Guide to the Harold C. Urey Papers 1932-1953
University of Chicago Library
Urey, Harold C. Papers
1932-1953
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Harold C. Urey was a physical chemist who won the Nobel Prize for the discovery of deuterium, served as Director of War Research for Columbia University's Atomic Bomb Project, then joined the University of Chicago's Institute for Nuclear Studies. This collection consists of scientific notebooks developed by Urey and his students, most dating from the mid-1930s and documenting research in isotope separation, an area in which Urey was the leading authority.
Information on Use
Access
Open for research.
No restrictions.
Biographical Note
Harold Clayton Urey was born on April 29, 1893 in Walkerton, Indiana. He received his Bachelor of Science degree in Zoology from the University of Montana in 1917 and a Ph.D. in Chemistry from the University of California in 1923. Following postgraduate work at Niels Bohr's Institute for Theoretical Physics, he taught at Johns Hopkins University, and was appointed Associate Professor in Chemistry at Columbia University in 1929. In 1934 he was awarded the Nobel Prize in Chemistry for the discovery of deuterium. He continued to research isotopic chemistry, and particularly the separation of isotopes.
Between 1940 and 1945, Urey served as Director of War Research, Atomic Bomb Project, at Columbia University, where he contributed to the Manhattan Project. In 1945, he moved to the University of Chicago's Institute for Nuclear Studies, becoming the Martin A. Ryerson Professor in 1952. His work at University of Chicago made major contributions to the field of geochemistry. He later went on to positions at Oxford and University of California.
Following World War II, Urey advocated arms control and nuclear safety, joining the Union of Concerned Scientists. Later in his life, he was involved in the U.S. space program as an advisor and consultant.
Urey's publication include Atoms, Molecules and Quanta (1930, with A.E. Ruark), and The Planets (1952), as well as numerous papers. From 1933 to 1940, he was editor of the Journal of Chemical Physics.
Scope Note
This collection consists of 17 laboratory notebooks developed by Urey and the students he mentored. Most of the notebooks date from the mid-1930s, immediately following Urey's discovery of deuterium and spanning the award of his Nobel Prize and further research in isotope separation at Columbia University.
Many of the students whose notebooks are included here made important contributions to their fields, both in their work with Urey and later in their careers. Represented here are Harry G. Thode, a prominent Canadian nuclear chemist and key figure in the development of McMaster University; Charles A. Bradley, with whom Urey introduced the Urey-Bradley force field; Weldon G. Brown, who went on to serve as a professor of organic chemistry at University of Chicago; and several others who performed significant research in isotope separation under Urey's mentorship.
The notebooks in Box 3 are not identified by the researchers who developed them, but are likely to be Harold Urey's own, or possibly those of his students.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Association of Oak Ridge Engineers and Scientists. Records
Atomic Scientists of Chicago. Records
Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists. Records
Chandrasekhar, Subrahmanyan. Papers
Darwin Centennial Celebration. Records
Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists. Records
Fermi, Enrico. Collection
Franck, James. Papers
Harrison, Roland Wendell. Papers
Simpson, John. Papers
Subject Headings
Urey, Harold Clayton; Isotope separation; Manhattan Project (U.S.); Chemists
INVENTORY
- Bradley, Charles A., "Thermal Conductivity Apparatus," 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Brown, Weldon G., "Fractionation of Carbon Isotopes," 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Daggett, A.F., "Record of Analysis of Samples from Heavy Water Plant I," 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- McLaren, James, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Myers, L.S., Jr., "Nuclear Studies," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Thode, Harry G., "Separation of Isotopes - Nitrogen," 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Thode, Harry G., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Urey, Harold C., "Solutions to Numerical Problems in MacDougall's Thermodynamics," n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Wahl, M.H., "Research," 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Wahl, M.H., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Weber, Lawrence A., "Concentration of Isotopes," 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Unidentified notebook, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "N2 and C Isotopes, Enzyme Activity Tests," 1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Unidentified notebook, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "Isotope Separation," 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Unidentified notebook, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "Gas Samples," 1948-1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)